*music*
Well, good morning, church.
So grateful for you all to join us on this rainy holiday weekend as we wrap up our series on the book of Jonah.
Hopefully you all have been as encouraged and challenged as I have as we've continued this story.
And we said from the beginning that it is a familiar story to many of us, but not as familiar of a text of Scripture.
Oftentimes we kind of deal with the story of Jonah and more pop culture descriptions of it,
which can miss the nuance of what the text of Scripture is actually inviting us to consider.
Because we've said the story is not really about a big fish.
It's not really about the Ninevites or even Jonah as much as it is about you and me and how we relate to God,
how we understand God's character and his invitation for us to participate in his world.
Everything in the text is upside down and exaggerated.
Everyone and everything, including the cows, obey God, except for the Israelite prophet,
the one that we would expect to be the obedient one in the text.
But he's so blinded by his nationalistic pride and his hatred for his enemies that he cannot see what God is inviting him into.
This is kind of where we've been through the last three weeks.
And today as we turn our eyes to chapter four, there's been some, throughout the first three chapters,
there's been some question as to whether or not Jonah is learning his lesson or not and what his motives are.
And chapter four is really going to give us the clearest understanding and unpacking of Jonah's sin,
of what it is that motivated all of his activity in chapters one through three.
He pretty much owns up to it in chapter four.
And so today my hope is that even though Jonah's kind of disobedience and sin is almost absurd to us in chapter four,
which is kind of the point, it's almost a comedy of errors to get us to realize how we participate with God the same way that Jonah does.
My prayer is that we will hear in our own stubborn rebellion, God's tender patience.
That we might be able to hear God whispering to us, inviting us to repent in the same way he invites Jonah too.
And we will end our gathering with communion.
It's in the back.
If you didn't get a chance to grab one of these on the way in, you've got 40 minutes or so to make your way back there.
So let's pray.
God, as our praise goes up, my prayer is that our walls will come down.
There's so many walls that we see in Jonah's life that keep him from surrendered obedience to your invitation.
And when we're honest with ourselves, God, we realize that there are so many walls in our own lives that keep us from genuine surrender and repentance and a receiving of your invitation in our lives.
And so, God, today I pray that our walls would come down.
Holy Spirit, I pray that you would speak to each one of us where we are at and the ways in which we participate in an invitation from you the same way Jonah does.
God, help us to see where our hearts align with Jonah's hearts.
And also, God, help us to see your tender mercy and compassion and patience with Jonah in the midst of his rebellion and sin.
And may we, God, hear for ourselves your invitation, gentle, patient whisper of repentance to us.
May we be a room full of people completely abandoned, surrendered to you for your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbors.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Well, we're going to be walking through chapter four, so if you want to follow along with me, I'd love for you to get your Bibles.
And just in preparation for next week, if you are a phone Bible person, good.
We're not Amish here.
We're not telling you that that's a sin.
But as we go into our next series on a digital detox, I'd encourage you to dust off your paper copies of the Scriptures and bring them with you so that you can kind of hold this in your hand.
I think it's good to do that.
So, thought experiment that I would love for you to join me in as we begin.
I'd love for you to try and recall the last time that you changed your mind about a strong opinion that you held.
And I'm not talking about, like, how early is too early to put up a Christmas tree or whether or not Die Hard is a Christmas movie, right?
Like, I know we have strong opinions about these things.
I'm not talking about when's the last time you changed your mind about one of those things.
But when's the last time you changed your mind about a strong opinion that you had on a weighty subject?
And my hunch is, it might be as hard for you as it was for me when I was preparing this message to come up with the last time you changed your mind about a strong opinion you had on a significant topic.
Which means one of two things.
It means this room is full of people that are extremely wise.
Which is option one.
Option two is that this room is full of people who are slightly more stubborn than we might like to acknowledge or admit.
And stubbornness is relatively harmless when it's over things like when we put up our Christmas tree or whether or not Die Hard is a Christmas movie or whether or not Android phones should even exist.
But it becomes far more dangerous when we're stubborn about ultimate things.
Like, who God is.
How he works.
And what he's inviting us into when he talks about his kingdom coming and his will being done on earth as it is in heaven.
Especially when our ideas, which my hunch is that all of our ideas about God, not all of our ideas, but all of us have ideas about God that are slightly misinformed or incorrect.
And this is where we see Jonah in chapter 4.
The author gives us a dialogue interaction between God and Jonah that clearly shows Jonah being foolishly stubborn and wrong in his view about who God is, what he's like, and what he's inviting Jonah to participate in.
And if by now I have stalled long enough for you to finally recall the last time that you changed your opinion on a strong, significant matter, my hunch is that it wasn't because you just lost a debate on Facebook to somebody that was smarter than you.
Rarely do we change our minds because someone smarter than us said something that confronted our ideas.
Oftentimes, most of the time, I find in my life that when I change my mind, when I have a strong opinion about a significant topic, it's because somebody drew near to me relationally.
But they invested in hearing my story, in hearing the reasons why I have the opinions that I have, and they've asked challenging questions.
And they've engaged with my ideas and helped me see things from a different point of view.
And this is the role that God plays for Jonah in Jonah chapter 4.
The God of the universe who created and sustains Jonah, the very breath in Jonah's lungs that he's using to fight with God,
God very easily could have smacked him in the back of the head and said,
you foolish, stubborn, rebellious prophet.
Don't you see your error, your bad ideas?
But that is not what God does.
God patiently and lovingly draws near to Jonah in relationship and asks him questions aimed at helping him see his flawed perspective.
And so my hope and my prayer is that as we read this text, we will hear the God of the universe doing the same to us,
drawing near to us in relationship and asking us questions about our strongly held opinions where we may or may not be smarter than he is.
So that's where we're headed.
Let's read the text and see where it takes us.
Jonah chapter 4 says,
But to Jonah, this seemed very wrong.
So the Ninevites have repented immediately after his very bad sermon, right?
His five-word bad sermon that really didn't mention much about God or repentance or anything.
It was just like, you're going to get destroyed.
The Ninevites, the people that you would expect to not repent, repent.
And Jonah's not happy about it.
To Jonah, this seemed very wrong.
And he became angry.
And he prayed to the Lord,
Isn't this what I said, Lord, when I was still at home?
This is what I tried to forestall by fleeing to Tarshish.
I knew that you are gracious and compassionate, slow to anger and abounding in love, a God who relents from sending calamity.
Now, Lord, take away my life, for it is better for me to die than to live.
But the Lord replied, just a gentle question from the God of the universe.
Is it right for you to be angry?
Jonah had gone out and sat down at a place east of the city.
There he made himself a shelter.
He sat in its shade and he waited to see what would happen to the city,
still hoping that God might change his mind and do the thing that he wants God to do.
And then the Lord God provided a leafy plant and he made it grow up over Jonah to give shade for his head to ease his discomfort.
Gentle, kind, patient.
And Jonah was very happy about the plant.
But at dawn the next day, God provided a worm, which chewed the plant so that it withered.
And when the sun rose, God provided a scorching east wind and the sun blazed on Jonah's head so that he grew faint and he wanted to die.
And he said, it would be better for me to die than live.
But God said to Jonah, is it right for you to be angry about the plant?
It is, he said, and I am so angry that I wish I were dead.
But the Lord said, you have been concerned about this plant that you did not tend or make grow.
It sprang up overnight and it died overnight.
And should I not have concern for the great city of Nineveh,
in which there are more than 120,000 people who cannot tell their right hand from their left,
and also many animals?
What a great way to end this book that we've been working through.
The book ends with, what about the cows?
I like it too.
Jonah is here in chapter four performing what I would call, in my expert opinion,
a good old-fashioned temper tantrum.
He's furious.
Why?
Because God did the thing that Jonah knew that he would do.
The last thing on earth that Jonah wanted him to do.
And I know that all of us have witnessed the temper tantrum before.
Likely in the aisle of the grocery store in front of us,
whether it's our kids or the kids in front of us in line.
We've all witnessed a temper tantrum.
And they usually look ridiculous to everyone involved,
except for the one having the tantrum.
Correct?
And this is what we see in Jonah.
This tantrum looks ridiculous to pretty much everyone involved.
Because in the moment of a tantrum,
the person having the tantrum can't see anything past their own perspective.
They can't see anything past their own desire.
All they can see is themselves and their opinions.
And this is exactly what the author of Jonah wants to expose for us in Jonah's life.
He has passionate opinions.
But these passionate opinions come from a limited perspective that disagrees with God's definition of truth
and causes him to rebel against God's authority over his life.
So I want to unpack those two limited perspectives with the rest of the time that we have.
His limited perspective causes him to disagree with God's definition of truth
and rebel against God's authority over his life.
So first, Jonah disagrees with God's definition of truth.
Jonah says, I knew you would show compassion to the Ninevites.
Subtext, I knew you would do the wrong thing.
This is what Jonah has in his mind.
At the heart of Jonah's rebellion is disagreement with how God chooses to define truth and run his world.
And he's not even trying to disguise it.
It's so obvious that he literally quotes Scripture back to God.
Did you guys hear this familiar text in Jonah chapter 4?
I knew that you were gracious and compassionate, slow to anger and abounding in love.
When you heard me read that, did that pop something in your head?
Where else does that text come from?
Does anybody know?
Psalm somewhere, okay.
Exodus 34 is the first time, right?
This is God's self-disclosed definition of himself to the nation of Israel, to Moses,
right after their own rebellion, right?
Their own idolatry.
God says, I am a God who is compassionate and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love.
But the interesting thing that we have here is the prophet, the Israelite prophet,
who likely had the text of the Torah memorized, only quotes part of the text back to God.
If you are familiar with Exodus 34 or you've grown up in the church, you've heard it in enough times.
The text goes on.
It says, I know you are gracious and compassionate, God, slow to anger and abounding in love.
Jonah stops.
The next phrase is abounding in love and faithfulness.
And that Hebrew word for faithfulness can also be defined as truthfulness.
And so Jonah is not even trying to hide the fact that he disagrees with God's definition of truth.
He says back to God, I know you've told us that you're a God who's compassionate, gracious, slow to anger,
abounding in steadfast love and truthfulness.
But I believe that you are a God who is all of those things except for truthful.
Because I don't agree with the way that you're choosing to define truth.
Instead, I think you're a God who doesn't care about justice, who doesn't care about truth.
Instead, you're a God who repents.
This is where Jonah stops quoting Scripture and adds his own commentary.
I guess he thinks because he's a prophet that he gets to add to the text.
And this is what he tries to do.
He says, you're not abounding in love and faithful.
You're abounding in love and you relent from sending calamity.
Some texts have it translated, you repent concerning evil.
Jonah here is calling God out on his definition of truth.
He's saying, you have said that you are true, but I say that you actually don't care about justice.
You don't care about the wickedness of the Ninevites.
Jonah is saying, you aren't truthful.
You're inconsistent.
You have to be merciful or just.
You can't be both.
And if you're going to try and be both, I'd rather be dead than live in a world that's run by you.
This is where we see Jonah interacting with God.
Literally, partially quoting Scripture and saying,
I don't agree with the way that you have chosen to define truth.
I'd rather define truth in my own image and from my own perspective.
You hear Jonah saying, I'd rather, if I have to live in a world where you're in charge, I'd rather die.
And ultimately behind that, he's saying, I think the world would be a better place if it was run the way that I think it should be run.
And although this example of Jonah is a bit ridiculous, I think if we're honest and self-reflective, we can admit that we've all had similar conversations with God.
We all have a limited and self-centered perspective that often causes us to question or even redefine truth for ourselves in the face of what God says is true about him.
We want a God who affirms our ideology and confronts the ideology of those we disagree with.
And like Jonah, we partially quote Scripture.
We pick and choose the passages of Scripture that allow us to create a God that is more like us than like the God revealed in the pages of Scripture.
And people on both sides of the religious aisle do it.
The religious zealous people obsessed with absolute truth and morality as they define it love to quote passages about Jesus flipping tables and making whips.
Telling sinners to go and sin no more while conveniently ignoring passages about taking care of the widow and the orphan and the immigrant.
Or passages like how you might want to take the log out of your own eye before you get hot and bothered about the speck in your neighbor's eye.
We quote the Scriptures that make us feel right and others wrong.
And when we come in contact with Scriptures that make us feel a little bit uncomfortable or like maybe we have slightly limited perspective on who God is and what he's like.
We try and contextually explain it away and make it fit our own agenda.
This is what Jonah is doing and this is what we often do.
Progressive proponents of postmodernism where all truth is relative and all paths lead to God.
These people, they love to quote Scripture.
They love to look at the teachings of Jesus and see how Jesus ate with sinners and how he told the Pharisees not to cast the first stone.
But they want to pretend that that same Jesus didn't say the words, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
And no one comes to the Father except through me.
Most of us are far more like Jonah than we'd like to admit.
We disagree with truth as God defines it.
We either want a God who's always truthful according to our definition and rarely merciful unless we're the ones who need mercy.
Or we want a God who's always merciful and less concerned with truth except for when those who define truth differently than us have influence or power.
It becomes an identity issue for us.
And what's interesting is that at the beginning of the book in chapter one, we heard the author introduce us to Jonah, son of Amittai.
And Amittai literally means truth.
And so Jonah has this identity, this identity issue at the core of who he is.
I am a person of truthfulness.
And how often does this happen to us where our definition of truth becomes our identity?
It becomes a clothing that we wear.
And whenever we come in contact with God trying to challenge our definition of truth, we can't get past it.
That's why I was so fixated on that, the worship song, let our walls come down.
Because our identity of what we define as right and wrong becomes these walls that we cannot hear God challenging us and convicting us in the midst of our sin.
And it's this disagreement with God's definition of truth that leads God to smack Jonah up the side of the head?
No.
It leads God to tenderly draw near to Jonah and ask one simple question.
Jonah, is it good for you to be angry?
Or to put it another way, a way that we might hear echoes of the Garden of Eden, Jonah, is it good for you to define good and evil for yourself?
This is the question that God is tenderly asking Jonah.
The prophet who has the Torah memorized, who knows what is at stake in the Garden of Eden.
People taking from God his ability to define good and evil and to rule the world in his way and trying to define good and evil for themselves.
And Jonah is doing the same thing that people on repeat have been doing since the beginning.
And God draws near to him, just like he draws near to Adam and Eve.
And just like he draws near to you and I when we are in stubborn rebellion and sin.
And he says, is it good?
Is it really as good as you think it is for you to be able to run the universe the way that you think it should be run?
Will this actually lead to the life that you want?
And as stubborn people often do when their bad intellectual ideas are challenged, Jonah doesn't even interact with God.
He says, talk to the hand.
He's not interested in a dialogue.
And so he leaves to the east side of the city, where I believe we see the second motivation of Jonah's temper tantrum.
The first is he disagrees with God's definition of truth.
And the second is he's rebelling against God's authority over his life.
Not only does he not want God's truth to be truth for him, because he disagrees with God's truth, he doesn't want God to have any authority over his life.
And just like we often do when we disagree with God intellectually, we flee from him relationally.
When we come in contact with a passage of Scripture that challenges our definition of God, how often is it that we actually run away from him relationally?
I was thinking about this this week.
There's this kind of Christian culture thing that's been happening for a long time.
It's kind of exited the vogue of Christian culture, but you may have heard of it deconstruction.
You guys heard this concept of people deconstructing their faith.
And oftentimes at the heart of deconstruction is people go away to college or they get sucked into some ideological argument about why the God of the Bible is not a good God.
And why, you know, it goes against all morality that we define for ourselves.
And so we come to grips with this intellectual idea that causes us to question the way that God defines truth.
And what happens is often because we question God's truthfulness, we flee from him relationally.
And going east, which is what Jonah does, the Scripture says that he goes to the east of the city.
This is a literary motif that has been developed throughout the book of Genesis that represents people moving away from God's presence and ultimately trying to recreate Eden apart from God.
This is when the original recipients would have heard him going east of the city.
They would have heard this pattern that is repeated throughout Genesis from the fall to Cain to Babel to Sodom.
All of these people are moving east from Eden, further and further away from God's design, his good presence.
And we're trying to define and create Eden for ourselves apart from God's presence.
We're trying to define truth for ourselves and we're trying to create a world in which we can rule and reign without God's authority in our lives.
So he goes to the east away from God's presence and he builds for himself a shelter.
The same word here for the tents or the booths that God commanded Israel to live in once a week for the Feast of Tabernacles.
They were made out of leafy trees and myrtle and palm and they were to remind Israel that God is at work seeking to restore Eden even now in the midst of our failure.
And so the Israelites, Jonah being one of these, who had participated in the Feast of Tabernacles his whole life,
he knows about living out in a tent for a week to remind him that God is faithful and that God is at work restoring Eden in the midst of the brokenness of humanity.
And instead, Jonah goes out and he builds himself a tent.
He doesn't want God's authority over his life anymore.
He wants to create authority for himself.
Once again, we are far more like Jonah than we'd like to admit.
When we find ourselves disagreeing with God's definition of truth, we often flee his presence and try and recreate the blessing of Eden apart from the presence of God.
We look for comfort and pleasure from God's creation outside of God's definition of how his creation should be used.
And our limited perspective causes us to rebel against God and his authority over our lives.
We want the blessings of Eden without the presence of God.
which leads God, again, to smack Jonah right upside the back of the head like he deserves.
No.
It leads God to once again tenderly, patiently confront Jonah with a lived parable.
This is like Jesus style parables before Jesus came about and started doing parables.
God puts Jonah in a situation where he has to have a lived experience that can go beyond his intellect and to his heart.
This is God doing exactly what the people who drew near to you relationally that helped you change your mind about a strong opinion that you had.
This is exactly what God is doing here.
He's not, he's no longer engaging Jonah's mind.
He knows that that's not going to work.
He begins to engage Jonah's heart.
And God appoints, or as the NIV translates it, provides a plant to grow up over Jonah to provide shade.
Jonah already had some shade.
He built for himself a tent and God says, hey, I can build a better tent.
I can do it overnight at the snap of a finger or the speaking of a word.
I'm going to bring a plant over top of you.
And the text says, he made this leafy plant grow up over Jonah to give shade for his head, to ease his discomfort.
The thing that I love about this is that word for discomfort can also mean evil.
This is such a sophisticated text of Scripture.
The author is literally, he puts this ambiguous word here.
So we're not actually sure what the leaf is doing.
Is the leaf providing comfort for Jonah or is the leaf confronting Jonah's evil actions of running away from God and planting a garden for himself in the desert?
Or is it doing both?
Which I think what God does here, he draws near to Jonah and he provides comfort for him.
But the comfort that he provides for him is also going to engage his heart with his bad ideas that have lead him to rebellion and evil.
And at last we see our grumpy, self-righteous and disobedient prophet happy for the first time in all of the Scripture.
It says that he is exceedingly glad, he's very happy about this plant that he has received from God.
This undeserved mercy of God on his life makes him extremely joyful.
And the next thing God does is he appoints a worm to eat the plant.
And an east wind that seems to not only have blown the plant, the dead plant away, but it seems to have blown the tent that Jonah created for himself away.
And so now Jonah is sitting east of the city in the desert with no shade, completely uncomfortable.
And it takes two verses for him to go from finally being happy to being miserable.
And yet again, ready for God to kill him.
And this word here, appoint, or as the NIV translates it, provide, is the same word about God providing the fish to swallow Jonah.
God is appointing things to try and get Jonah's attention.
Each time he appoints something after Jonah rebels, after Jonah leaves and does the thing that God told him not to do,
God appoints something to try and get his attention.
It's something that looks uncomfortable and difficult, but it is ultimately trying to lead him to life.
And so just a small side point I want to ask us is, is it possible there's some things in our lives that are uncomfortable,
that are difficult, that are challenging, that in some ways look like they're a response to the bad decisions that we've made.
Is it possible that God is appointing some things in your life to try and get your attention and draw you back into relationship with himself?
The God of the universe, who Jonah has disagreed with, ignored, and ran away from, continually and patiently re-engages Jonah in relationship.
And God revisits the same question he asked Jonah earlier, but with a slight twist, no longer engaging his intellect, but instead his emotions.
He says, is it right for Jonah's attention, finally gets Jonah to begin to engage with him.
And Jonah's really mad.
This is the height of his temper tantrum.
He says, of course it is good for me to be mad about this plant, so mad that I wish I were dead.
So, what do you all think about that question?
Is it good for Jonah to be mad about the plant?
Nice try, Peyton.
I appreciate the effort.
I appreciate the boldness to speak out.
I actually, I think it's great for Jonah to be mad about the plant.
It's just not good that Jonah's mad about the plant and doesn't care about people.
And this is what God is trying to get his attention on.
You're mad about the plant.
You have pity over the plant that you did not plant and did not water, and that's good.
But if that's good, don't you think it's okay for me to pity an entire city of people created in my image?
And this becomes the question that the author of Jonah wants each of us to ponder.
Not as if we're asked, not as if it were asked to Jonah, but as if it were directed to us.
Even in the face of our disagreement with how God chooses to run his world, with how he allows suffering and pain to continue.
With how seemingly people who rebel against him get blessed, while others who are surrendered to him face the difficulty and suffering of a fallen world.
God tenderly whispers to us, do you think it's okay if I get to decide what it looks like for me to be compassionate and gracious?
Slow to anger and abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness.
Or in other words, is it right for the creator to define truth and rule his world the way he sees fit?
And the next question underneath that becomes for us, are we willing to submit to that?
This is what I think that the ending of Jonah wants us to ponder is, is it good for God to get to rule his world his way?
And are we willing to submit to it?
God tenderly confronts our desires to disagree with his truth and take his throne.
This is the story of, this is how the story of Jonah ends.
God tenderly confronting us when we don't like his definition of truth.
And when we don't want his authority over our life, we don't see him smacking Jonah over the head.
We see him tenderly and compassionately and patiently drawing near to Jonah.
And the theme of, I feel like the theme of this entire series for the past few weeks has been,
you and I are far more like Jonah than we realize or like to admit.
We run from God's invitation.
We disagree with his definition of truth and we resist his authority in our lives.
Trying to produce a life with the blessings of Eden apart from the relational fatherly presence of God in our lives.
And I think it's good for us to be confronted with this reality.
But as we end the series, I want to intentionally make a shift where we take our eyes off of ourselves and our own propensity to be like Jonah.
And just for the rest of our time today, I just want us to shift our eyes back to God who patiently and lovingly pursues us.
Pursues Jonah, pursues you, and who pursues me.
Not only are we far more like Jonah than we realize or admit, but God is far more gracious than we typically give him credit for.
I mean, just look at how he treats the Ninevites.
A city who is in complete rebellion, who it says, don't know their left from their right, who are the enemies of God's people.
God shows them compassion and grace.
Just look at how he treats Jonah, the rebellious and self-indulgent prophet.
God, through the book of Jonah, confronts our hypocrisy, our bigotry, and our idolatry.
But he does so tenderly with both whales and worms, all to get our attention so that we might hear his gracious invitation.
Is it right for me, the creator of the universe, to define truth and rule my world as I see fit?
And are you willing to trust that?
Jonah wants a God who is just but not merciful unless he needs mercy.
And others oftentimes want a God who's merciful but not just unless their definition of truth is at stake.
And the God of the Scriptures has this incredible way throughout all of human history of being equally both.
He's not a God of justice or mercy.
He is a God that provides mercy through his justice.
And as we end the gathering, I want us to meditate on this reality by preparing to take communion together.
And as we prepare to take communion together, I want us to meditate on two verses from Jonah chapter 4.
And Jonah's frustration with God refusing to give the Ninevites justice.
He states,
Jonah knows that God has a track record of repenting from sending calamity.
He knows because the first time that God said the verse that Jonah quoted back to him,
God was showing mercy to Jonah's people.
Who had just constructed a golden calf and had a real weird religious service that involved lots of immorality and debauchery and drunkenness.
And God was compassionate and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness.
Jonah knows that God often withholds his justice and his wrath.
And in God's speech to Jonah at the end of the book, he says that the Ninevites are a people who do not know their right from their left.
And with those two texts in mind, I want to make the argument that this is the gospel.
That each one of us are like the Ninevites who do not know our right from our left.
We have a limited perspective and we want to define good and evil for ourselves apart from God.
And God, who would be just to punish us, instead is eager to repent from sending judgment.
And he does so for the Ninevites and for us the same way.
Through the death, burial, resurrection, and ascension of Jesus.
That's what Romans 3 is all about.
Romans 3, verse 25 says,
For God presented Jesus as the sacrifice for sin.
People are made right with God when they believe that Jesus sacrificed his life, shedding his blood.
This sacrifice shows that God was being just.
He was being fair when he chose to hold back punishment for those who had sinned in times past.
Paul has the Ninevites in mind here as he writes this text.
God withheld judgment from the Ninevites because of Jesus.
He withholds judgment for us because of Jesus.
For he was looking ahead and including them in what he would do in the present time.
God did this to demonstrate his righteousness, his mercy and justice perfectly balanced with one another.
Not mercy or justice, but mercy through justice.
God did this to demonstrate his mercy through justice for he himself is fair and just.
He makes sinners right in his sight when they believe in Jesus.
God is eager to repent from calamity in exchange for grace, but it requires that we be eager to repent from our sin and turn to him in faith.
God is eager to repent from the Lord.
All of the judgment and suffering decided for each of us fell.
The judgment and suffering of the whole world fell on Jesus at the cross.
I love this line.
In reality, God's repenting in the face of man's repentance is Jesus Christ.
God is patient and tender, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness.
And we see that balance of love and faithfulness at the cross of Jesus.
And so this morning, if you are a follower of Jesus,
I would encourage you to prayerfully consider participating in the bread and cup,
which is a reminder for us, a regular reminder for us,
that all of God's promises find their yes in Jesus,
that all of God's mercy in the old covenant found its justice in Jesus,
that all of God's mercy to us in our rebellion and sin finds its justice in Jesus,
that all of the suffering and eternal consequences that we deserve for our rebellion was placed on Jesus.
And so when we partake in his body and his blood,
we remember that God is compassionate and gracious,
slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness.
God doesn't forsake justice.
He places the justice we deserve onto Jesus.
So if you're a follower of Jesus,
I encourage you to take Christ's body broken for you.
Take Christ's blood shed for you.
As I was thinking about this message, the old hymn came to my mind.
Now it's gone from my mind.
Earnestly, tenderly, Jesus is calling.
Calling for sinners.
Come home.
And so if you're in a spot where you find yourself like Jonah,
either disagreeing with how God chooses to run his world,
or rebelling against his authority over your life,
my prayer is that you would hear an invitation from the Father this morning.
Come home.
Is it good for you to define good and evil for yourself?
Or is the God of the universe who made you and sustains the very breath in your lungs?
Is he worthy to be surrendered to?
And for others of us who find ourselves frustrated and angry at people that we disagree with?
People outside the walls of this church who don't,
who don't believe in God, who don't think highly of the gospel,
who think the Scriptures are foolish.
My question for you is, is anger and disagreement and good arguments intellectually going to do anything to change that person's mind?
Or might God be inviting you to take the tactic that he takes with you?
And might we engage people who think the Scriptures are foolish,
who thinks God is unjust or unkind or doesn't exist.
May the invitation for us be to extend a hand of compassion and love to those people.
To hear their stories.
To ask thoughtful questions.
And to let God be God.
I think so much conflict happens because Christians try and make people believe what they believe.
When in reality, God is just inviting us to relationally engage with people who don't know their right from their left.
And not to judge them or condemn them for that, but to ask them questions.
And give them space to think about whether or not there might be a God who created and sustains the universe.
And whether or not he might be trustworthy for them to surrender their lives to.
So, Father, we just, we pray for people all over this room.
I don't know each person's circumstances, but I'm sure there are people that are in rebellion to you.
That are having conversations with you where they're frustrated and disagree with the way in which you're allowing things to happen in their life.
I pray this morning, God, that they would hear your tender whisper.
And that they would look to the cross and realize that through the cross you are, you have demonstrated yourself worthy to be surrendered to.
And God, for those of us that have had conversations with people that we disagree with recently.
Or we get angry and frustrated and try and convince them that they're wrong and we're right.
God, would you give us your heart for them.
The way we see it demonstrated to Jonah that you are patient and kind.
That you're not intimidated by people's rebellion and disagreement.
God, may we be your hands and your feet to people who disagree with us.
So that your kingdom might be more clearly displayed on earth as it is in heaven for your glory, for our good and for the good of our neighbors.
It's in Jesus name I pray.
Amen.
Prayer tent is available if you would like it.
And go in peace.
Go in peace.
Thank you.